<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<project xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xmlns:s="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:g="http://splitcells.net/gal.xsd" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
         xmlns:e="http://splitcells.net/sen.xsd" description="compatibility and portability">
    <objective>
        <objective>Find out, if this works efficiently and effectively.</objective>
        <objective>Write documents and programs in one language i.e. documentation as code.</objective>
        <objective>The idea is to model syntax trees like XML and JSON
            via the Perspective class.
        </objective>
        <objective>This base language could make it easier to apply automatic refactoring via the
            Java's IDEs, to apply custom checks via Java's type system and runtime systems.
            This also makes it possible to integrate document with the program code much easier
            by linking from data to source code.
        </objective>
        <objective>Ensure this via an Example document, that this is indeed a good idea.
            <objective>Needs to be fully compatible to XML and JSON.</objective>
        </objective>
        <objective>Introduce this by migrating to this system.
            <toDo>Create a program that translates XML or Text to this Perspective model.</toDo>
            <objective>XML and JSON still need to be supported,
                but should be used for secondary content or for rendering only.
                Also the acceptance for such a system will not be good, so XML, XSD, XSL and JSON
                should still be supported.
            </objective>
        </objective>
    </objective>
    <scheduling>
        <priority>
            <queue>
                <toDo>Use DemTest as a testing ground.</toDo>
                <toDo>Create an example class, because the formatting seems to be a problem,
                    according to experience.
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create a testsuite which states all requirements to the Perspective in order
                    to support data as source code.
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create a framework in order to support data schemes.</toDo>
            </queue>
        </priority>
    </scheduling>
</project>