<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet attribute="text/xsl" href="xofi.html.xslt"?>
<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd"
	xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd"
	xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd sew.xsd">
	<meta>
		<title>Origin of The Project Generic Allocator</title>
		<description>This post explains how the Gel project came to light.
		</description>
		<publication_date year="2017" month="04"
			day_of_month="22" />
		<related_to>
			<url>
				<site_instance_purl />
				/2016/10/11/projects
			</url>
			<url>
				<site_instance_purl />
				/2015/03/04/about-this-site
			</url>
			<url>
				<site_instance_purl />
				/2016/10/12/project-generic-allocator
			</url>
		</related_to>
		<arbitrary_publication_date />
		<license>standard</license>
	</meta>
	<chapter>
		<title>Universal Allocation Program</title>
		<paragraph>
			The idea of this project originated from an internship
			during my
			studies of computer science. During the internship the
			assignment
			problem solver
			<link>
				<text>Universal Allocation Program</text>
				<post>/2015/04/20/universal-allocation-program-manual</post>
			</link>
			was
			developed. This program had two purposes.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>First of all it had to assign pupils to a set of courses
			where each pupil had one or more preferred courses. Additionally, the
			number of pupil in each course was limited. Each course which took
			place also had to have more pupil than specified by a certain
			threshold.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The second goal of the program was to provide an expressive
			problem model. This was tested with a second problem. The task was to
			schedule exams of pupils. The problem could be modeled by the
			program. Unfortunately, the program was not able to solve it because
			a more advanced solving algorithm than present was
			needed.
		</paragraph>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>A Fresh Start via the Generic Allocator</title>
		<paragraph>The goal of my master thesis was to create a new framework
			for
			assignment problems that had an improved problem model and
			superior
			solving routines compared to the Universal Allocation
			Program.
			Three
			scheduling problems of schools were used in order to
			validate the
			framework. Two of the problems were optimally solved for
			the given
			test cases. The third problem was nearly solved but in the
			end correct
			solutions were not produced (for a given problem instance
			about 5 out
			of 508 assignments were done incorrectly). In addition,
			each problem
			required its own solving routine.
		</paragraph>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>The Rewrite of the Generic Allocator</title>
		<paragraph>After getting my master's degree in computer science I
			wanted to learn more about solution problems, artificial
			intelligence(AI) and programming. Therefore, I have created this
			hobby project in order to organize my learning process in this field.
			The framework of my master thesis (which is used as the project's
			name) is recycled for this undertaking. Unfortunately the foundation
			of the framework needs some improvement which in practice leads to a
			rewrite of the framework.
		</paragraph>
	</chapter>
</article>