<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd" xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd">
    <meta>
        <!--
            SPDX-License-Identifier: EPL-2.0 OR GPL-2.0-or-later
            SPDX-FileCopyrightText: Contributors To The `net.splitcells.*` Projects
        -->
        <title>Splitcells Network's Objective</title>
        <d:toDo>
            Add the symbiosis project to the objectives, when the project is mature enough.
            <item>The <link post="/net/splitcells/symbiosis/index">symbiosis project</link> is a philosophical discovery of the open source nature of this project in relation to society.
            </item>
        </d:toDo>
    </meta>
    <chapter>
        <title>Primary Goals of The Splitcells Network Project</title>
        <paragraph>
            We provide an open source ecosystem centered around optimization and operations research,
            in order to achieve the following:
        </paragraph>
        <list>
            <item>Provide software and documentation to create and optimize problems based on a simple but powerful assignment model.</item>
            <item>
                Empower people to model and reason about complex systems,
                built out of interconnected optimization problems.
            </item>
            <item>Enable the user to understand the results given a solver and an optimization system.</item>
            <item>Develop new optimization algorithms.</item>
            <item>Provide compatibility between different optimization systems.</item>
        </list>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Subprojects to Achieve The Primary Goals</title>
        <paragraph>
            The <quote>Splitcells Network</quote> is the overarching project,
            that brings everything together and establishes general project guidelines.
            The following is a list of subprojects,
            that demonstrate how the general goals of the project are fulfilled:
        </paragraph>
        <list>
            <item>The<link post="/net/splitcells/cin/objectives">Crisis Network</link>module enables extraordinary complex models and their optimization.
            </item>
            <item>The<link post="/net/splitcells/gel/objectives">Generic Allocator</link>is the foundation for models and their optimization.
            </item>
            <item>The<link post="/net/splitcells/network/community/projects/2024-04-06-school-organization-project">School Organization</link>project targets to make the software actually usable.
            </item>
            <item>The <link post="/net/splitcells/gel/ui/objectives">Gel UI</link> provides a code editor, in order to use the software's functionality without special tooling.
            </item>
            <item>The <link post="/net/splitcells/symbiosis/perspective/guidelines/perspectives.html">Discovery Trees</link> provide an overarching semantic inventory system. (
                This has no dedicated project yet and is part of the Symbiosis project.
                This should probably be a subproject of the Network project.
                Also, see `src/main/java/net/splitcells/dem/object/Discoverable.java` and `net.splitcells.shell` for info regarding existing implementations.)
            </item>
        </list>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Guidelines and Decisions Relevant for The Primary Goals</title>
        <paragraph>The following list makes the approaches for reaching the objectives more focused and concrete:
        </paragraph>
        <list>
            <link post="net/splitcells/network/guidelines/inherently-broken-and-rotten-by-design">Inherently Broken and Rotten by Design</link>
            <item>Ensure, that the software is reliable for its users.</item>
            <item>The project's relationship to the public is unclear, but stays an unresolved issue.</item>
        </list>
    </chapter>
</article>