<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd"
         xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd sew.xsd">
    <meta>
        <!--
            SPDX-License-Identifier: EPL-2.0 OR GPL-2.0-or-later
            SPDX-FileCopyrightText: Contributors To The `net.splitcells.*` Projects
        -->
        <title>
            <siteName/>'s Guidelines
        </title>
        <description>
            These are the guidelines for the Splitcells Network project.
            Do not consider these code guidelines for your own code.
            <link>
                <text>If you do, people will hate you, and you’ll be scorned by
                    friends and family.
                </text>
                <url>https://git-scm.com/book/en/v1/Git-Branching-Rebasing#The-Perils-of-Rebasing
                </url>
            </link>
        </description>
        <publication_date year="2018" month="04" day_of_month="29"/>
        <d:toDo>
            <d:todo>Make all assumtions visible (i.e. nullable variables via Optional).</d:todo>
            <d:toDo>Fork, join and cathedral development protocol.</d:toDo>
            <d:toDo>Programs should be primarily seen as tree/table transformers in order
                to simplify programming paradigm and language use.
            </d:toDo>
            <d:toDo>Make it possible to tolerate out of date documentation.</d:toDo>
        </d:toDo>
    </meta>
    <chapter>
        <title>Goals</title>
        <paragraph>Guidelines describe, how something should be done or what the guiding principles are.
            It makes actions more reproducible and predictable.
            Guidelines are nothing more and nothing less.
            If these guidelines are overridden a reason should be present,
            and be documented or commented, if it is feasible.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>These guidelines refer to the Splitcells Network project.
            These guidelines do not handle communities and other social interactions.
            The management Communities and co. has to be done by themselves.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>For (programming) languages and document formats prefer
            using the most official or the most common guidelines,
            if there are no guidelines of this project applying to the
            aspect in question.
            In other words, language and documentation specific guidelines
            of this project try to only override public guidelines instead of
            writing complete custom guidelines from scratch.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Base Rule</title>
        <paragraph>The project and its parts should be portable, extendable, adaptable,
            <link>
                <text>deletable</text>
                <url>https://programmingisterrible.com/post/139222674273/how-to-write-disposable-code-in-large-systems
                </url>
            </link>
            and comply with
            <link>
                <text>Perspective's guidelines</text>
                <post>/net/splitcells/symbiosis/perspective/index</post>
            </link>
            .
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>The compliance with the
            <link>
                <text>Perspective's guidelines</text>
                <post>/net/splitcells/symbiosis/perspective/index</post>
            </link>
            specifically means,
            that the file and content path of a particular information
            (for an XML element,
            this would be the file path + the XPath pointing to the XML element)
            should identify and describe or at least summarize the content's
            meaning.
            This also means, that in an ideal case, one should be able to guess,
            where to look, for a particular content without knowing where
            the files are located
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
</article>