<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet attribute="text/xsl" href="xofi.html.xslt"?>
<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd"
         xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd sew.xsd">
    <meta>
        <title>Guidelines for Discovery based Perspectives</title>
        <description></description>
        <publication_date year="2020" month="01" day_of_month="06"/>
        <license>standard</license>
        <d:toDo>
            <d:toDo>Create Definitions at index page of project.
                <d:toDo>discovery based Networks of Perspectives and Changes</d:toDo>
            </d:toDo>
            <d:toDo>Implementation guide lines for concepts.
                <d:toDo>Implement tree set representation.
                    <d:toDo>Implement via construction tree.</d:toDo>
                    <d:toDo>Implement via builders.
                        <d:toDo>Implement via named arguments.</d:toDo>
                        <d:toDo>Implement via fluent interface.</d:toDo>
                    </d:toDo>
                    <d:toDo>Implement overview features.
                        <d:toDo>Implement multiple interactions on same objects.
                        </d:toDo>
                        <d:toDo>Implement pipelines.
                            <d:toDo>Use for path set representation.</d:toDo>
                            <d:toDo>Use for function call chain.</d:toDo>
                        </d:toDo>
                    </d:toDo>
                </d:toDo>
                <d:toDo>Implement relation registry representation.
                    <d:toDo>Relation registry is a set of applications of predicates with multiple arguments.</d:toDo>
                    <d:toDo>Implement public and private attributes via 2 related objects representing public and
                        private parts
                        of object.
                    </d:toDo>
                    <d:toDo>RDF, OWL, SKOF, onthologies, thesaurus and relations in databases are examples of this.
                    </d:toDo>
                </d:toDo>
                <d:toDo>Implement access and linking.
                    <d:toDo>Function Argument Convention
                        <d:toDo>Lookup functions with certain type at nth argument.
                            Returns list sorted by the type of nth argument in hierarchy descending.
                        </d:toDo>
                        <d:toDo>Later arguments should preferably be related only to previous arguments or not at all.
                        </d:toDo>
                    </d:toDo>
                    <d:toDo>Implement relation via file location in folder structure as an alternative to direct and
                        explicit
                        linking.
                    </d:toDo>
                </d:toDo>
            </d:toDo>
        </d:toDo>
    </meta>
    <chapter>
        <title>Minimize Size of Perspectives</title>
        <paragraph>The smaller a perspective is, the easier it is, to split a perspective path
            in many smaller parts. This in turn makes it easier to construct such paths.
            Additionally this makes it easier to create a new branch of the path, with minimal changes.
            Furthermore, it gets easier and faster to select fitting children, when the size of the perspective is
            decreased,
            provided a fast evaluation of network traversal's direction.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>Therefore, perspectives that do not represent lists, should a have a minimal number of children of
            the same
            type. Perspectives representing a list, should only have elements of the same type,
            in order to make it clear, that these are lists.
            Thereby, perspectives, where it is hard to determine the searched path, are more separated from
            the rest of the network. This in turn makes the management of complexity more easy.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Path Specificity</title>
        <paragraph>The longer a path is, the more detailed and specific something is described by it.
            In other words the, the longer the path is, the smaller the set of things is that complies with the meaning
            of the path.
            This also holds true for links, as even absolute links can be or get incorrect over time.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Path's Meaning</title>
        <paragraph>The interpretation of the path element names should match the actually referenced object as close as
            possible.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Naming and Wording</title>
        <paragraph>Prefer words and names where there is no singular and plural version,
            as this helps to minimize the size of perspectives.
            Also prefer using only nouns, adjectives or verbs.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
</article>