<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd"
         xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd">
    <meta>
        <title>Project Life Cycle Guidelines</title>
    </meta>
    <chapter>
        <title>Life Cycle</title>
        <paragraph>It should be known, why a project is created and under which conditions it will be dismantled.
        </paragraph>
        <chapter>
            <title>Version Control</title>
            <paragraph>The commit log is a program, that describes the development of the project.
                The
                <link>
                    <text>semantic versioning</text>
                    <url>https://semver.org/</url>
                </link>
                is used as a default versioning format.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Make clear what is guaranteed and do this only via an explicit interface,
                that has no implementation specifics.
                Prefer backward compatible changes to backward incompatible changes.
                Make as much undefined as possible for not essential things in order to minimize the set of guarantees.
                Breaking other software, because it relied on implementation specifics is better,
                than breaking other software via incompatible API changes.
                Do not just break features, but also migrate its usage to other appropriate features before breaking
                said features.
            </paragraph>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Development Process</title>
            <paragraph>Do not assume that better skills, more intelligence, working harder, etc. automatically lead to a
                better result.
                Prioritize a working project state at every point in the development.
                Prefer test driven development.
                Ensure that the project is build, tested and executed in different environments,
                in order to ensure, that the projects works.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Every part of the development process should have a task</paragraph>
        </chapter>
    </chapter>
</article>