<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd"
         xmlns:d="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd sew.xsd">
    <meta>
        <title>Guidelines for Networks of Discovery based Perspectives</title>
        <description></description>
        <publication_date year="2021" month="02" day_of_month="05"/>
        <license>standard</license>
        <d:toDo>Support for rendering network as one long paths like a book
            can be very advantages.</d:toDo>
    </meta>
    <chapter>
        <title>Network Discoverability</title>
        <paragraph>Every path to a specific perspective in the network can be viewed as a story of discovery:
            travelers wandering through the network searching for their destination.
            Everyone has their target(s).
            Some know what they are looking for.
            Some of them are walking through the network aimlessly, searching for their meaning in life.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>The root perspective of the network should be the gateway to heaven for these souls.
            It should accommodate everyone's reasonable needs.
            In other words, any reasonable list of questions suitable for searching a desired perspective
            in the network, should correspond to a path in the network.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Globalization</title>
        <paragraph>Globalization is the act of minimizing the number
            of networks or making it easy to translate, connect and traverse such network clusters.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>It is often not possible, to make a single global unified network,
            that is valid for everyone.
            This is often not needed. Instead, one can use shared global networks,
            where each network has its own root perspective and therefore path space.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>Every non-global network can just link to these globally shared networks.
            The root perspectives of each network needs to isolated in such a way,
            that these are not mixed.
            This ensures that paths are unambiguous and can be shared across networks.
            Thereby, networks can be integrated.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>Generally speaking, the number of networks, should be minimized
            in order to have minimal cost of optimizing and using the networks.
            Nevertheless, one has to keep in mind, that each actor/project needs its own root perspective
            and therefore network. It may be enough to use virtual networks.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter><title>Namespace</title>
        <paragraph>All paths starting of the network's root node,
            are the namespace of the network.
            Each path acts as a unique identifier of the namespace.
            This can also be called root namespace in order to differentiate it from virtual namespaces.</paragraph>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Virtual Namespace</title>
        <paragraph>A virtual namespace is a prefix shared by multiple paths,
            where the last element of the prefix is the root node of the namespace.
            All paths starting from this root node represent the virtual namespace.
            The concept of virtual namespaces can be used in order to store multiple networks inside one.
            </paragraph>
        <paragraph>Consider <quote>splitcells.net</quote> for instance:
            <quote>https://splitcells.net/net/</quote> is the root namespace of the site,
            whereas <quote>https://localhost:8445/net/splitcells/website/minimal/</quote> contains a copy of the site,
            but with a different theme.
        </paragraph>
    </chapter>
</article>