<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<project xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xmlns:s="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:g="http://splitcells.net/gal.xsd" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
         xmlns:e="http://splitcells.net/sen.xsd" description="compatibility and portability">
    <solution>
        <priority>
            <queue>
                <toDo>Define a minimal Java EBNF grammar via "java.code.verify" and antlr.
                    <toDo>Create Grammar.</toDo>
                    <toDo xl:href="https://github.com/antlr/antlr4"/>
                    <toDo>Check only files, which are not part of the bootstrapping implementation.</toDo>
                    <idea>
                        <toDo>Remove dependency injection and only have basic configuration via static immutable
                            variables in order to simplify code for translation.
                        </toDo>
                        <toDo>Create an project to reintroduce dependency injection after the translation
                            project is working.
                        </toDo>
                    </idea>
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create a translator that translates the program to Dlang,
                        because Dlang is very similar to Java und allows functional side effect free programming.</toDo>
                <toDo>Create a way to automatically generate the skeleton of environment integration code.</toDo>
                <toDo>Translate Dem to a Lisp langauge.</toDo>
                <toDo>Translate an actual project to a Lisp langauge.</toDo>
                <toDo>Remove reflection code.
                    <toDo>Generic configuration class can be implemented via a tree/stack
                        of config class and thereby removing the need for type mapping.
                    </toDo>
                    <toDo>Let Gel's table columns just use one common type
                        in order to omit downcasting.
                    </toDo>
                </toDo>
            </queue>
            <unscheduled>
                <toDo>Learn OCaml.</toDo>
            </unscheduled>
        </priority>
    </solution>
    <objective>Ensure that a software project's dependencies like language, framework and platforms
        are easily replaceable. The replacement can be automatic or manual.
        <solution>Ensure that the software project is valid and only uses certain features,
            that makes it easy to migrate the project.
            <toDo>Standardize usage of Java feature by defining a subset of valid Java grammar and checking it.
                <toDo>Use different Grammar for Dem and subsequent projects,
                    because Dem is the base for subsequent projects, which should have higher restriction.
                    <toDo>Only some parts of Dem should use a different/unrestricted part.
                        This part should only be the Java-specific code.
                    </toDo>
                </toDo>
            </toDo>
            <toDo>Ensure that the code is easily translatable to other languages with minimal effort and manual work.
                <idea>Support different paradigms.
                    <toDo>Object-Orientation mainly provides polymorphic tree transformations.
                        Dlang seems to be a good choice.</toDo>
                    <todo>Support a very simple and basic version of functional programming
                        with an simple statically typed object system.
                        The object system, which is kind of an OOP-System only provides state interfaces.
                        The functions define the state transitions of the objects.
                    </todo>
                </idea>
                <objective>Always translate code to other language automatically and test it, in order to be sure
                    that the code is portable.
                    <toDo>Create a translator which translate other projects to a different language.
                        The translator only has to translate projects complying with this project (compatibility and portability).
                    </toDo>
                    <result>This would allow to check additional properties of the program before running it.</result>
                </objective>
            </toDo>
        </solution>
    </objective>
</project>