<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<project xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://splitcells.net/den.xsd" xmlns:p="http://splitcells.net/private.xsd"
         xmlns:s="http://splitcells.net/sew.xsd" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:g="http://splitcells.net/gal.xsd" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
         xmlns:e="http://splitcells.net/sen.xsd" description="compatibility and portability">
    <objective>
        <objective>Find out, if this works efficiently and effectively.</objective>
        <objective>Write documents and programs in one language i.e. documentation as code.
            <objective>The idea is to model syntax trees like XML and JSON
                via the Perspective class.
            </objective>
            <problem>How to document methods and functions?
                Name can be linked via annotations and static final Strings.
                Each document has to be linked to a package/path, attribute and argument path.
            </problem>
        </objective>
        <objective>Use automatic refactoring capabilities of Java IDE in order to automatically refactor code and
            documents.
            <problem>Refactoring of XML via XSL or custom tree processing code is not hard.</problem>
        </objective>
        <objective>Ensure this via an Example document, that this is indeed a good idea.
            <objective>Needs to be fully compatible to XML and JSON.</objective>
        </objective>
        <objective>Introduce this, if it suits, by migrating to this system.
            <objective>XML and JSON still need to be supported,
                but should be used for secondary content or for rendering only.
                Also the acceptance for such a system will not be good, so XML, XSD, XSL and JSON
                should still be supported.
            </objective>
        </objective>
    </objective>
    <scheduling>
        <priority>
            <queue>
                <toDo>Translate XML documents via XSL automatically to Perspective code.
                    <toDo>Create XSL</toDo>
                    <toDo>Create example translation.</toDo>
                    <toDo>Format code XSL acceptably.</toDo>
                    <toDo>Translate files in folder structure recursively.</toDo>
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create an example class, because the formatting seems to be a problem,
                    according to experience.
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create a testsuite which states all requirements to the Perspective in order
                    to support data as source code.
                    Use DocumentTest as basis.
                </toDo>
                <toDo>Create a framework in order to support data schemes.</toDo>
            </queue>
        </priority>
    </scheduling>
</project>